<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Comfort for parents, mourning over their hopeful children, that dye young In a funeral discourse upon Jer. 31. xvii. And there is hope in thine end, saith the Lord. By Thomas Whitaker, minister of the Gospel at Leeds, in York-shire.</title>
            <author>Whitaker, Thomas, 1650 or 51-1710.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65690</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221995</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833235</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833235</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37710</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65690)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37710)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2162:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Comfort for parents, mourning over their hopeful children, that dye young In a funeral discourse upon Jer. 31. xvii. And there is hope in thine end, saith the Lord. By Thomas Whitaker, minister of the Gospel at Leeds, in York-shire.</title>
                  <author>Whitaker, Thomas, 1650 or 51-1710.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 109, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for John Dunton, at the Raven, in the Poultrey,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Tightly bound, with some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Jeremiah XXXI, 17 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37710:1"/>
            <p>Comfort for Parents, Mourning over their Hopeful Children, THAT DYE YOUNG. In a Funeral Diſcourſe upon
<q>
                  <bibl>JER. 31. xvii.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And there is Hope in thine End, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Whitaker,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Leeds,</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Dunton,</hi> at the <hi>Raven,</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:37710:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37710:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>AT the Deſire of Mr. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Dunwell,</hi> who was particularly concerned, both for the Preaching and Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the following Sermon, I write this Preface. In his <hi>Hopeful Child</hi> he ſaw many Pleaſant and Amiable things, but now that dear Comfort of his Life, being withdrawn, as he acquieſces in the Holy Providenee of God, that
<pb facs="tcp:37710:3"/> cauſes many times thoſe Flowers to wither by an Early Decay, which perhaps we ſhould be very apt to doat upon; ſo he doubts not but this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, made by that Miniſter, under whoſe Inſtructions he ſits with great Delight, will contribute to the Good of others, eſpecially thoſe who are yet in the Morning of their Age.</p>
            <p>I could not in Civility refuſe the prefexing my poor Name, ſuch as it is, tho' the worthy Author needs no Recommendation, much leſs mine; his Skill in Spiritual Affairs, and the Succeſs wherewith God has bleſt his zealous Eudeavours for the Good of Souls, render it needleſs for me
<pb facs="tcp:37710:3"/> to ſay any thing that hath ſo much as the Shew of Flattery; he neither expects it, nor does my <hi>Genius</hi> lead me to ſay much of one who is too mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt to hear his own juſt Praiſes, and who has ſo many Witneſſes of his fitneſs for his Honourable Work a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Numerous and Happy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory, which was, I doubt not, Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied at the Hearing of the following Sermon, and will be more ſo at the Reading of it; it muſt be their own fault if they receive not conſiderable Benefit from a Subject, ſo ſuited to the uſe of <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi> and which is ſo well managed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37710:4"/>
            <p>I ſhall only ſpeak a little to thoſe that are <hi>Young,</hi> and to thoſe <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> who are ſhedding Tears for the Loſs of <hi>Hopeful Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe that are <hi>Young</hi> have but little Experience of the Sorrows and Calamities of Life; and in a World, where they have been for ſo ſhort a ſpace, every thing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to them as Gay and Fine; they are but beginning to Travel, and finding no Pain nor Trouble at preſent, promiſe to themſelves many ſmooth Years, and to be at eaſe a long while; and being Charmed and Blinded with ſenſual Pleaſures, they put afar off the <hi>Evil Day.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:37710:4"/> But I would deſire them to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that they may be taken away betimes, that their <hi>Sun</hi> may be Cloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a little after be is riſen, and that now in their full Strength and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor it is the moſt proper ſeaſſon, wherein to prepare for another World; and if they ſhould live to be old, they'll find no Inconveniencies from ſuch an <hi>Early Preparation.</hi> it will be the Joy of their <hi>Parents,</hi> and their own Joy; God will mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply his Favours, and he will be pleaſed to ſee them in his <hi>Vineyard</hi> in the <hi>Dawn of Life;</hi> this will ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them to run their <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Race with an eager haſte, and the
<pb facs="tcp:37710:5"/> Brightneſs of their Examples will allure others to run for the ſame <hi>Bleſſed Crown;</hi> whereas, if they be ſecure, careleſs, and unthoughtful of Eternity, their Minds will be laid waſte, and be like the Field of the Sluggard, all overgrown with Thorns and Bryers, with every evil and unpleaſant thing: This Earth with its fair Charins and Tentations, will chain them to its ſelf, and the Devil will lead them Captive at his Will; he will inſult over them in their grow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing Age, and ſtrive to keep them from deſerting his Service when they were before his Volunteers. And it muſt be a doleful, and Melancholy Proſpect
<pb facs="tcp:37710:5"/> to their poor <hi>Parents</hi> to ſee their dear <hi>Children</hi> run in the way of Hell, and like to be the fuel of <hi>Eternal Flames.</hi> I would beg of them to read this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and other good Diſcourſes, that may give them a right ſenſe of things, and eſpecially to delight in the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> the frequent peruſal of which will keep them from the Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Youth,</hi> and with admirable Clearneſs and Efficacy direct them to cleanſe their ways, and while they read in ſo Divine a Book, to pray to the great Father of Lights, that he would irradiate their Souls with Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Beams, that they may not only ſee the Light, but feel the warmth of
<pb facs="tcp:37710:6"/> Truth; and then, if they die early, if they go to Bed betimes, they'll fall aſleep in Jeſus, and never complain that they were in Heaven too ſoon; if they be good, 'tis no great matter whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Lamps be extinguiſhed at Midnight, or at Noon.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>Parents,</hi> who have loſt good <hi>Children,</hi> whom they loved with all imaginable Tenderneſs, tho' it is impoſſible for them not to ſhed tears at the pleaſant Images of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their pretty Carriage, their little innocent Actions, their ſerious Diſcourſe, and their Holy Prayers, yet they have a great many things to ſweeten the bitterneſs of their Grief.
<pb facs="tcp:37710:6"/> Oh what a Spiring is it of daily Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, to think, that <hi>a part of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves is in Heaven!</hi> And that tho' <hi>Death</hi> has pluckt from their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, a Child, that was ſo Amiable and ſo good, yet inſtead of groaning under the miſeries of Life, he is praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God above with Loud and Chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Hallelujahs:</hi> How reviving muſt it be to think that the Supream Ruler, whoſe, they and theirs are, has removed the ſweet Flowers that they look'd upon with Joy, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Coel ſtial Paradiſe!</hi> It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving to think that theſe little Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels are filled with an Early Glory, and gone to ſee the Face of their
<pb facs="tcp:37710:7"/> 
               <hi>Heavenly Father,</hi> as their Angels did before, the Parents of ſuch Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ought not to ſhed unprofitable Tears, for all their Sorrows will not cauſe a Spring in the Grave, nor make the lovly plants to grow again: They ſhould not alway keep their Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger on the Sore; for the Rod that chaſtens them is dipt in Honey, and managed by a Father's Hand, who muſt be more to them than many Sons and Daughters: Their Love to theſe Amiable things ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld not exceed their Love to God; he muſt be more to them than their Life, which yet is a dearer and ſweeter thing than all their other Comforts: What Graces ſoever adorned the Bodies of their
<pb facs="tcp:37710:7"/> 
               <hi>Children,</hi> what Perfections ſoever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched their Souls, yet it ſhould ſupport them to think that whilſt they are left to many a Cold and Stormy Winter, they whom they once loved, are arrived at their home; and tho' they ſee them no more in their Families, yet they ſhall meet them with Pleaſure at the Great Day, and never part again; and then thoſe Bodies which the Grave for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon preyed upon, ſhall be like the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Body of our Lord. You that are <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> may Lawfully drop ſome tears o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Graves of your departed <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> but you ought not to bury your ſelves alive, nor to be made unſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to God by exceſs of Grief. You prayed that they might be good, and
<pb facs="tcp:37710:8"/> they were ſo; you prayed that they migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> get to Heaven and they are gon thither<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> only you <hi>Mourn</hi> that they are there ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoon. Weep not for them, but for you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelves; you may live to ſee diſma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> times, and heavy Judgments, which ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> occaſion a general Amazement and Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſternation; and which may make man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Mother ſay, <hi>Bleſſed is the Wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that never bear, and the Paps tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> never gave Suck.</hi> Remember that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time is ſhort, and it ſignifies little, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one Roſe wither in the Morning, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> another in the Afternoon, ſeeing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> will certainly decay. If you ſee ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dye in the Bud, and in the green o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Youth, you muſt be ſatisfied, tho' yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> begg'd that they might not be gather'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:37710:8"/> till they were laden with a great deal of <hi>Fruit.</hi> It must comfort you to think that they are like the <hi>Early Dew,</hi> exhaled to <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> betimes, though the ſhining Drops are vaniſhed. Theſe young Heirs of Glory peep'd into the World, they ſaw nothing here but Vexation, Sin and Miſery, and ſo they went out again. If you ſay we <hi>Mourn</hi> for our Loſs, as being a ſad Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of <hi>Wrath</hi> againſt us, we are afraid our <hi>Children</hi> were taken away from us in Anger; but is it not a Teſtimony of Love to deliver any out of Pain betimes, and not to ſuffer them to Languiſh very long? Thoſe that God has dearly loved have died ſoon; the firſt Perſon that went to <hi>Heaven</hi> died in the Flower of his Age, even <hi>Abel,</hi> the Righteous, ſo did <hi>Abijah, Joſiah,</hi> and our Excellent King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>VI.</hi> Theſe all died Young; <hi>and was it an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument</hi> of <hi>Divine Diſpleaſure</hi> to let them
<pb facs="tcp:37710:9"/> Conquer and Triumph almoſt as ſoon as they began to <hi>Fight,</hi> whilſt others must endure the heat of the Day, and many a furious Combat, e're they march from the <hi>Field of Battle?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That God would by his own <hi>Gracious Preſence</hi> ſupply the want of all outward <hi>Comforts</hi> to thoſe who are bereaved of their <hi>Dear</hi> and <hi>Hopeful Children,</hi> and that he would Bleſs this <hi>Sermon,</hi> and the <hi>Author,</hi> and that he may long ſhine in the Sphere where he is placed, for the Good of many <hi>Souls,</hi> Is the hearty De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Timothy Rogers.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37710:9"/>
            <head>Comfort for Parents, Mourning over their <hi>Hopeful Children,</hi> That <hi>Dye Young.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>JER. 31. XVII.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And there is Hope in thine End, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE two great Supports of a Chriſtian in this Vale of Tears, are a lively Faith, and a ſteady Hope. For, as a Chriſtian's higheſt Happineſs lies within the Vail, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.</note> ſo <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> alone can give him a Comfortable Proſpect of what Senſe and Sight cannot yet reach unto.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:37710:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>They minister a ſingular Support, both in Life and Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the greateſt Troubles of <hi>Life,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.10,11.</note> 
               <hi>Faith</hi> in the Perſpective of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, can ſpy Light thro' the darkeſt Cloud: And <hi>Hope,</hi> being encouraged by <hi>Faith,</hi> can wait with Patience for an happy Iſſue.</p>
            <p>In the Approaches of <hi>Death, Faith</hi> can caſt its Eagle-Eye over this Dead Sea, unto the Fragrant Mountains of Spices beyond: <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12.</note> And <hi>Hope</hi> can ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the Thoughtful Soul with a Gracious Expectation, that a few Moments will waft it ſafe over the Gulph, and make it Poſſeſſor of thoſe Glorious Manſions.</p>
            <p>Does God ſend his grim Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, <hi>Death,</hi> to ſummon our ſelves to come away? It's an Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, beyond Expreſſion, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.15.</note> to have <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> lead us through the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37710:10"/> dark Paſſage, till <hi>Faith</hi> be Convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Viſion, and <hi>Hope</hi> advanced into Fruition.</p>
            <p>Is it our dear Relations or Friends, that God ſends the tremendous Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to? What a bleſſed Staſt of Support is it to the Surviving <hi>Mourners,</hi> when we have <hi>Hope</hi> in their <hi>Latter End?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Departing Soul can venture comfortably upon, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4.</note> and walk chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully thro' the Gloomy Valley of the Shadow of <hi>Death,</hi> when attended with two ſuch Refreſhing Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> truely ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Promiſes of the <hi>Word,</hi> and the Experience of a Gracious Principle in its own Heart.</p>
            <p>And we that ſurvive, can part with our <hi>Dying Relations,</hi> with a more chearful Reſignation, when we are encouraged with ſome Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37710:11"/> Grounds of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope:</hi> That their Departure hence is but their happy Paſſage into a far better <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Accordingly, This is the very Conſideration, which a Gracious God Adminiſters for the Support of the <hi>Mourners</hi> in the Text.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>And there is Hope in thine End, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>In opening the Words, we ſhall conſider:
<list>
                  <item>1. The Primary and Litteral Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of them.</item>
                  <item>2. What Practical Improvement may be made of them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We ſhall take a ſhort look into the Primary, Original Senſe of the words. For the underſtanding where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, you need only to have Recourſe unto <hi>v.</hi> 15. of the Chapter, where you have <hi>Rachel, (i. e.)</hi> The poor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37710:11"/> Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> (who were Deſcendents from <hi>Rachel</hi>) Mourning for her Children, becauſe they were not.</p>
            <p>A great many of them were very probably cut off by the Fatal ſtroke of <hi>Death,</hi> and the reſt were ready to be carried away Captive into <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> which was as a civil Death: Upon which doleful Occaſion, this Bereaved Tribe breaks out into a moſt bitter Lamentation; the Ditty of whoſe Mournful Elegy was, <hi>That her Children were not; There were loſt and gone, and ſhe was like to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy them no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to ſtem the Tyde of theſe Swelling Waters of <hi>Mara,</hi> God ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably ſuggeſts this Relieving Ground of Comfort in the Text, <hi>There is Hope in thine End, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:37710:12"/>
            <p>The Senſe whereof amounts to this purpoſe: Why doſt thou Mourn, as one utterly undone, or as one, whoſe Caſe admits of no <hi>Relief,</hi> or <hi>Comfort?</hi> Tho' thou be as a Deſolate <hi>Mother,</hi> bereaved of her Children, yet there is <hi>Hope,</hi> both reſpecting thy ſelf, and reſpecting thoſe, whom thou concludes to be utterly loſt and gone. Thoſe that are Dead, and muſt return to this <hi>Life</hi> no more; if they be tranſplanted to a better, what Reaſon is there to indulge an Immoderate Sorrow for them?</p>
            <p>And thoſe that are carried into Captivity, and ready to be put into their diſmal Graves in <hi>Babylon;</hi> they ſhall have a ſeaſonable Reſurrection, and ſhall return unto their own Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in due time, which may be a ſufficient Ground of Conſolation as to them.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37710:12"/>
            <p>This being the Literal Import of the Words, we come now,</p>
            <p n="2">2. To conſider what practical Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement may be made of them, with reſpect to Caſes of a like Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Now, in order hereunto, you may obſerve from the Account that's already given; that the Words are a Supporting Cordial, reach'd forth by the Compaſſionate <hi>Hand of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> to <hi>Diſconſolate Parents,</hi> bleeding over the Loſs of their <hi>dear Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tho' there may be a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable difference in ſome Particulars, betwixt the Caſe in the Text, and other Caſes, that may bear ſome Proportion thereunto; yet from the general Deſign of the Words, we may (without any great Force) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce from them this uſeful Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:37710:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> That it is a Soveraign Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to ſurviving Parents, under the Loſs of their <hi>Departed Children;</hi> That there is <hi>Hope in their Latter End.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Children</hi> are Parts and Branches of ourSelves; OurSelves are multiplied into ſo many leſſer Sprigs; yea, our own very Bowels ſpun out into ſo many ſmaller Threads: And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, when theſe, by an Irreſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Hand,</hi> come to be rent and torn from us; it cannot but be very Grievous to Innocent, and much more to Corrupted Nature.</p>
            <p>But when there is a well-ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Hope</hi> in their <hi>latter End;</hi> when there is a good Foundation to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <hi>That they are made Brahches in Chriſt, before they are pluckt away as Branches from our Selves:</hi> That there are ſome Lineaments of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37710:13"/> New Creature formed in them, before they are call'd off the Stage of this Old <hi>Creation:</hi> This cannot but open a Refreſhing Spring of Conſolation, to <hi>Mournful Parents,</hi> to aſſwage their ſwelling Sorrows, and to ſtanch their bleeding Wounds.</p>
            <p>In the management of this Point, we ſhall endeavour to ſhew.
<list>
                  <item>1. What are thoſe Symptoms, which may adminiſter good Ground of <hi>Hope,</hi> with reſpect to our <hi>dying Children.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. In what Reſpects this is ſuch a Soveraign Support, to Surviving <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> and <hi>Relations.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. What are thoſe Characters, which may adminiſter good Ground of <hi>Hope,</hi> with reſpect to our <hi>dying Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not here concern my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with thoſe <hi>Children,</hi> that die
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37710:14"/> in their Morning-Infancy, and are ſnatch't from their <hi>Mothers,</hi> or <hi>Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> Breaſt, by that time they are well come into the World; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, are no more capable of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erting any Acts of Grace, than they are of Reaſon. The Occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires not, and the Time will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me to engage in that Subject.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall confine my ſelf to ſuch <hi>Children,</hi> as have arrived to ſome Competent years of Underſtanding, and ſo are in a Capacity of leaving ſome Intimations of the early Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>Divine Grace</hi> upon their Hearts, altho' cut off in their Early Blooming days.</p>
            <p>Yet in our Management hereof, it becomes us to exerciſe all humble Sobriety, it being attended with ſome difficulty, to ſtate aright the firſt Sproutings of <hi>Divine Grace</hi> in Adult
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37710:14"/> Perſons, and much more in <hi>Young Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhall therefore make an Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, only ſo far, as the <hi>Line of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> without offering any Violence to it, will conduct us, and leave the more Intricate Secrets of <hi>Divine</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, to him that beſt underſtands them, even to God himſelf: Who can diſcern <hi>Grace</hi> in thoſe Minuter Workings, which lie beyond the Reach of our Obſervation.</p>
            <p>To come to Particulars:</p>
            <p>There are theſe timely Intimations of Goodneſs in <hi>Children,</hi> which may miniſter good Grounds of <hi>Hope,</hi> with reſpect to their <hi>latter End.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. A Teachable Diſpoſition in the Things of God. As it is the unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable Duty of <hi>Parents</hi> to teach their <hi>Children</hi> betimes, and prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to inſtil <hi>Divine Truths</hi> into their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37710:15"/> Minds, as ſoon as they are capable of learning; ſo it is a very <hi>hopeful</hi> Indication in <hi>Children;</hi> when they are Teachable in <hi>Divine things,</hi> and chearfully receptive of <hi>Spiritual In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions</hi> in their tender Years. <hi>Whom ſhall I teach Knowledge,</hi> ſays God, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.9.</note> 
               <hi>whom ſhall I make to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Doctrine? Them that are weaned from the Milk, and drawn from the Breaſts.</hi> I know, the Words are deſignedly a very cutting Rebuke to the Unteachable <hi>Jews;</hi> intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that a weaned Child was as teachable as they: But withal, we may make this Obſervation from them, That when <hi>Children</hi> are ſo early receptive of Gracious Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, it is an Argument, That God is at work with them, as their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Teacher.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:37710:15"/>
            <p>To hear <hi>Children</hi> ſtudiouſly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive into Spiritual things, and asking good Queſtions about Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Heavenly Matters: To ſee them leaning their Heads, and lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Ears, earneſtly to liſten to Diſcourſes about Soul-affairs, and things of everlaſting Moment; what a Comfortable Proſpect muſt it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford! And as it cannot but be very Affecting to the Hearts of concerned <hi>Parents;</hi> ſo it can be eſteem'd no leſs than an hopeful Intimation in thoſe tender Plants: That God is dealing with their Hearts in their Morning-years, tho' in a way and manner undiſcernable to us.</p>
            <p>Who is it that forms the Heart, which by Nature is Crooked and Perverſe, into this Spiritual Docible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.1.</note> but he who has all Hearts in his Hand, and can mould them,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37710:16"/> when and how his Soveraign Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs pleaſes? <hi>Children</hi>'s Hearts in their Natural State, are lockt up againſt <hi>Divine things,</hi> as well as other Men's: And who is it, that opens the Lock ſo early, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.7.</note> but <hi>be that has the Key of</hi> David, <hi>and opens where none can ſhut, and ſhuts where none can open.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, A Teachable Mind, in an Age of Life, that's oftentimes the moſt untoward and Indocible, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies an Heart, touch'd with the Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>Heaven;</hi> And where God has his Hand upon the Spring ſo ſoon, it cannot but ſuggeſt a good <hi>Hope</hi> (through <hi>Grace</hi>) unto Thoughtful <hi>Parents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. An Affectionate Reſpect to the Holy Scriptures, is another ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Intimation of an <hi>hopeful</hi> Import. It's recorded as one of the Morning-Bloomings
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37710:16"/> of <hi>Divine Grace</hi> in a young <hi>Timothy,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>That from a Child he was acquainted with the Scriptures.</hi> His early Acquaintance with them implies his early Affection to them. He was ſuch an early Proficient in them, becauſe he had an early De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire unto them, and delight in them: which can be attributed to no other than a Divine Original.</p>
            <p>When Children therefore expreſs an early Reſpect to the <hi>Holy Bible,</hi> and love frequently to converſe with thoſe <hi>Bleſſed Oracles;</hi> when they take pleaſure in Reading them themſelves, and in hearing others Read them; when they make a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Remark upon ſignal Paſſages, and inquire into the Meaning of them, and lay them up as a choice Treaſure in their Hearts; when they love to Read ſuch Paſſages over
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37710:17"/> and over again, and to be telling of them, as if their Hearts were great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected with them, and ſuck't ſome Vertue and Sweetneſs from them; what Conſtruction can all this admit of, but as an <hi>hopeful</hi> hint from <hi>Heaven,</hi> of ſome Gracious Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings in thoſe tender Years.</p>
            <p>Is it not an Intimation, That the ſame <hi>Spirit of Grace and Truth,</hi> that indited the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> has begun to draw ſome Lineaments of thoſe <hi>Bleſſed Truths</hi> upon ſuch <hi>Childrens Hearts?</hi> When the <hi>Heart</hi> is much in the <hi>Bible,</hi> it's an Argument, there's ſomething of the <hi>Bible</hi> in the <hi>Heart:</hi> There's ſomething within anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Truths</hi> without, which gives them ſuch a pleaſant Taſte and Reliſh to the <hi>Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:37710:17"/>
            <p>There's ſome Minims of the Law writ in the Heart, though the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters as yet be but very ſmall, and ſcarce diſcernable. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10,11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This alſo may afford a very Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting Foundation of <hi>Hope,</hi> to Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Parents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A Towardly Inclination to Religious Duties, is another Token of an encouraging Nature. What a doleful Sight is it, and worthy of the moſt compaſſionate Reſentments, to obſerve the wretched Auk ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſome <hi>Children</hi> to Religious Exerciſes! Do but compare them then, with what they are at other times; and they are never more fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or more prone to Sleepineſs, than at ſuch Seaſons. How appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently do their Spirits enther ſink or fall, or grow croſs and ſour, upon the Management of any Holy Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37710:18"/> Thereby manifeſting their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Diſreliſh of, and prevailing A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſs, unto things of a Spiritual Heavenly Character.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, when <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> evidence a pleaſant Towardli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Holy ways of God; when they manifeſt a dear Affection to Prayer, and reading good Books, and Religious Diſcourſe, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and managed by others; and when they frame themſelves to theſe things, in what Manner and Meaſure their ſhort Capacity will admit; making up in the Will wherein they come ſhort in the Work: This is alſo a very Amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Hopeful Symptom.</p>
            <p>It's left as a Mark of Honour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on young <hi>Joſiah, That when he was but Eight Years old, he walked in the ways of his Father</hi> David, <hi>to do that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37710:18"/> which was Right in the Sight of the Lord.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 22.1,2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>What a lovely Diſcovery was it of an Immortal Seed, dropt into the Heart, when it thus began to ſprout above Ground! How delightful were ſuch early and choice Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings! The Power of <hi>Divine Grace</hi> muſt be at work betimes, where the Effects were ſo Early and Signal.</p>
            <p>Well, It miniſters no leſs matter, both of <hi>Delight</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> to ſee our <hi>Children</hi> beginning to ſavour the things of God, and to diſreliſh their Childiſh Vanities, in the timely Spring of their Day. And it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but beſpeak a new <hi>Divine Palat,</hi> formed in the Soul, to which the Vanities of Youth are ſo unſavoury, and the Exerciſes of Heaven ſo Grateful and Pleaſant.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37710:19"/>
            <p n="4">4. A Thoughtful Concernment about an Eternal State, is another hopeful Indication of early Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Childhood is a Time of Life, that ordinarily runs ſo much into Froth and Vanity, that it ſeldom admits of any ſerious Conſideration. How difficult is it to faſten a ſerious Thought upon <hi>Children,</hi> either of their Duty or Danger, either of their <hi>Preſent State,</hi> or <hi>Future Doom!</hi> Their Vain Minds are poſſeſs'd with their Childiſh Trifles, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11,10.</note> that there's no Entertainment for Thoughts, or Fears, or Cares of an higher Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: They are ſo charmed by the preſent Allurements of Time, that they know not how to apply their Minds to the more ſolemn Concerns of Eternity: And therefore, where any Thoughtfulneſs appears of this kind, it is the more remarkable.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:37710:19"/>
            <p>For <hi>Children</hi> to be poſſeſs'd with an Awful Senſe of an Eternal State; to hear them inquiring, <hi>What they ſhall do to be ſaved;</hi> to ſee them concerned about <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> muſt be much more than the ſame things in grown Perſons: It's the more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in them, by how much it's the more rare, and more contrary to the Temper of that Fooliſh Age. It's rare to have a Child's Mind com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to any thing, and much more to things that lie ſo remote from Senſe and Fancy, which are their chief Governing Principles.</p>
            <p>Whence then muſt theſe Thoughts have their Original? To what Spring muſt they be aſcribed? Certainly to no other, than the ſecret Operation of <hi>Heaven. Children</hi> do not uſe to look into their Graves, or take a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37710:20"/> Proſpect of Eternity, but when the Finger of the Almighty powerfully directs them thither: They do not uſe to entertain themſelves with Anxieties about another World, or what will be their ſuture State there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but when ſuch Thoughts are dropt from above. And how ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom do ſuch Thoughts abide, but when they are rivetted by the ſame Hand that made the firſt Impreſſion?</p>
            <p>When therefore Thoughts of this Nature take up ſuch early Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Minds and Hearts of <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> it is a Token of very comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Signification.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A real Deſire after an Intereſt in Chriſt, is another Intimation, that affords a good Ground of refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Hope.</hi> What an Encouraging Preſage doen it ſuggeſt, to hear <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> timely inquiſitive after the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37710:20"/> Bleſſed Jeſus; asking, <hi>who and what is he, and of what uſe to the Souls of Sinners:</hi> And upon Intelligence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, to be mighty ſollicitous and concerned about an Intereſt in his <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Mercy!</hi> Our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himſelf, who was no Stranger to the early Appearances of <hi>Divine Grace,</hi> lays it down as a fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Maxim: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 17.3.</note> 
               <hi>This is LIfe Eiernal, to know the only God, and Jeſus Chriſt, whom he hath ſent:</hi> It's Eternal Life in the Seed, though not in the Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; in the Beginnings, though not in the Perfection of it. The firſt Buddings of Spiritual, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of Eternal Life, are frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly couched in Pleaſing Inclinations, to hear of this Incomparable Perſon, and in ſecret Deſires to have a Part and Lot in him.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:37710:21"/>
            <p>And this argues both ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of a loſt State by Nature, and alſo ſome Spiritual Acquaintance with the Nature, Uſes, and Ends of Jeſus Chriſt, as the great Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of <hi>Heaven,</hi> for ſaving Periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Souls. Why do ſuch Souls e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem it their concern to look after a Saviour, but that they are in ſome meaſure ſenſible of their guilty, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done Condition, by reaſon of Sin? And why do they deſire to be inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted, and wrapt up in the Mercies of a Gracious Jeſus, but that they have had ſome Beam of <hi>DivineLight</hi> breaking into their Minds, whereby to underſtand him, <hi>as the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation, ordained of the Father for Guilty Sinners?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You muſt allow for the Incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Children,</hi> in not coming to that diſtinct Acquaintance with Chriſt,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37710:21"/> which maturer Years may arrive un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: But it is a ſingular Foundation of <hi>Hope,</hi> when they know ſo far of themſelves, as to be afraid of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a Natural State; and ſo far of Jeſus Chriſt, as to breathe out their Hearts in an Affectionate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment for a Portion in him, as the only <hi>Saviour of dying Souls:</hi> And more may be wrapt up in a Sigh, a Groan, a Word, a Tear of theirs to this purpoſe, than we are aware of.</p>
            <p n="6">6. A tender Fearfulneſs of known Sin, is another hopeful Teſtimony of early Goodneſs. We muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed make allowance for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballaſted Temper of Childiſh Years, which cannot be expected to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together free from the Vanities and Follies of that Age: But when <hi>Children</hi> are under powerful Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37710:22"/> of Fear of doing any thing, which they are convinced to be downright Sin; and this not ſo much from a Servile Awe of the Rod, as from an ingenuous Tenderneſs of Heart; it cannot but ſuggeſt a good <hi>Hope,</hi> notwithſtanding ſome Childiſh Follies, that they may be incident to.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Children</hi> cannot be ſuppoſed to have that explicite and extenſive Knowledge of Sin, that riper Years may attain unto. But what they underſtand to be Sin, they are ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, it's offenſive to God, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to their <hi>Godly Parents,</hi> as well as Damning to their own Souls; and from all theſe Conſiderations are poſſeſſed with an Awful Fear of doing amiſs: Who can eſteem this any other than a <hi>Divine Spark,</hi> ſtruck from <hi>Heaven</hi> into their Hearts, while yet in their tender Minority?</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:37710:22"/>
            <p>How fearful have ſome <hi>Children</hi> been in Lying (tho' an Iniquity too commonly incident to that Age) of taking the Name of God in vain, of profaning the Sabbath, or bearing apart in the wicked Exceſſes, that other <hi>Children</hi> run into? How con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious have ſome been to reprove their Fellows, that have been invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in theſe and ſuch like Vices, and that to the Admiration of ſuch as have obſerved them! How careful have ſome been to avoid the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of thoſe that could not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed from their early Prophaneſs? They have had no mind to Play, or Converſe, or keep Company with ſuch, tho' under many Temptations thereunto: What Conſtruction can be made of this early Tenderneſs, but that it is ſome line or ſtroke of the <hi>New Creature,</hi> drawn in the Heart
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37710:23"/> of ſuch young ones; which may juſtly encourage <hi>Parents</hi> to entertain a Comfortable <hi>Hope</hi> concerning them?</p>
            <p>It's obſerved, as a Character of a Gracious Import in the young King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 22.19.</note> 
               <hi>That his Heart was tender,</hi> When Conſcience is ſo early impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the Senſe of Sin and Duty; it is a good Sign. It's taken notice of, as an early Appearance of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this young Prince, and it is the like in others, where-ever it is found, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40.</note> 
               <hi>Being a Branch of that Fear, which God hath promiſed to put into the Hearts of his own People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. An Obediential Regard unto <hi>Parents,</hi> is another Argument for Good. As it is a frequently-repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Charge upon <hi>Children,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>To obey Parents in the Lord;</hi> ſo it is a very Promiſing Intimation, when they are early affected with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37710:23"/> of their Duty in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
            <p>Diſobedient <hi>Children,</hi> as they are the Grief and Heart-break of their <hi>Parents</hi> for the preſent, ſo they ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally give but a very poor Proſpect of <hi>Hope</hi> for the future, eſpecially when their Diſobedience is attended with Contempt and Obſtinacy. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly it is very obſervable, that among the Perſons, whom the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were to pronounce Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, upon <hi>Mount-Ebal,</hi> Contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, Undutiful Children are ſet, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in the very Front of the Black Catalogue. Next to the Idolater, that Maketh and Worſhippeth any Graven or Moſten Image, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 27: 16.</note> is <hi>He that ſetteth Light by his Father and Mother.</hi> And what blacker Mark of <hi>Infamy</hi> and <hi>Hopeleſneſs</hi> can be put upon any Perſons, than to be ſet in the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37710:24"/> of ſuch, as the Curſe of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> is upon? To bear any Place in that miſerable <hi>Beadroll,</hi> is ſad enough: But to be the very ſecond Rank of the Accurſed Crew, beſpeaks the Caſe to be particularly dreadful and diſcouraging.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, dutiful, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient <hi>Children,</hi> as they are the Joy and Crown of their Parents, while they live, ſo they give very good Ground of <hi>Hope,</hi> when they come to die; <hi>For they are the Children of Promiſe:</hi> And if they have not the Promiſe made good to them in a long Life upon Earth; it cannot but be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably hoped, that a Gracious and Faithful God will fulfil it in that which is better, even Life everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Heaven. I know the Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Acts of Obedience may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from different Springs or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37710:24"/> whichmay often vary the caſe. A Child may yield outward Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from Fear, as well as from Love. The dread of the Rod may overawe them, when Love, and the Senſe of Duty does not incline them; and in that caſe we cannot make ſo hopeful a Concluſion: But when a Child's Obedience evidently ſprings from an Obediential Diſpoſition; when it is influenced not ſo much by a ſlaviſh awful Fear, as by Principles of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, Love and Reverence; Love and Reverence to <hi>Parents,</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to the Command of God; it cannot but be reckon'd a very en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging Symptom. It's recorded to the Honour of our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>That he was Subject to his Parents. Tho'</hi> the Advancement of his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature into the Perſon of the Son of God, advanced him above
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37710:25"/> any Obligations of that kind, yet to teſtifie how natural, how amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, how becoming Obedience to <hi>Parents</hi> is, himſelf yielded all the Subjection and Obedience that could be expected from the Relation. He was Subject, that was Lord over all; to leave a bleſſed Example to <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> to be, and do likewiſe: And it cannot but be eſteemed an Hopeful ſign, to be conformable to ſo good a <hi>Pattern.</hi> It's a part of the Image of the bleſſed Son of God, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29.</note> to which all the <hi>Children of God are predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated to be conformed:</hi> And any Branch of Conformity to that Image cannot but afford a good <hi>Hope</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe in whom it is found.</p>
            <p>Do you ſee then, <hi>Children</hi> giving all becoming Proofs of their inward Acknowledgment of, and Venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for their <hi>Parents?</hi> Do you ſee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37710:25"/> them careful to pleaſe, and fearful to offend and grieve them? When other <hi>Children</hi> are Proud and Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machful, and Self-will'd; impatient either of Advice or Reproof; Do you ſee theſe liſtning to their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi>'s Exhortations, and melting un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Reproofs? When others make no matter of diſobeying and offending, and provoking their <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents;</hi> Do you ſee theſe efflicted and grieved at themſelves for grieving theirs? When the Obedience of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers laſts no longer, than while their <hi>Parents</hi> Eye is over them; Do you ſee theſe bear a tender reſpect to their <hi>Parents</hi> Pleaſure and Favour, as well from under, as while they are under their <hi>Parents</hi> Eye? In a word, Do you ſee them Fearful of, or Penitent for any thing, that looks like Undutifulneſs? Such <hi>Children</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:37710:26"/> but be lookt on, as leaving a good <hi>Testimony</hi> behind them, tho' ſnatcht away in their Morning-age.</p>
            <p n="8">8. A particular Love to good People, is another hopeful Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in <hi>Children.</hi> That Love to the Saints is made an evidence of <hi>Grace</hi> in Adult Perſons, is ſo plain in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> that nothing can be plainer. Particularly, it's the Mark mainly inſiſted upon by the Beloved Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>John;</hi> whoſe own Heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much affected with Love to God, and the <hi>Brethren,</hi> he makes this a Principal Tryal, with reſpect to others. I need not point to all the places that occur in his Epiſtles to this purpoſe, That one is enough<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>We know, that we are paſled from Death unto Life, becauſe we love the Brethren.</hi> Obſerve, he lays it down, not meerly as a probable, but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37710:26"/> as a Damonſtrative Argument. We know, that is, with an <hi>Holy Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> and <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> that we are paſſed from <hi>Death</hi> unto <hi>Life,</hi> from a <hi>State of Sin,</hi> unto a <hi>State of Grace,</hi> becauſe we love the <hi>Brethren;</hi> that is, the <hi>Children of God,</hi> as ſuch, or under that Conſideration and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter. And, as this is a Character ſo expreſs in <hi>Scripture,</hi> ſo in Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience it has been ſo ſingularly uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that it has ſupported the <hi>Spirits,</hi> and quieted the Fears of many doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Souls,</hi> when all their other <hi>Graces,</hi> not being ſo perceptible in their Operations, have been able to afford them little or no Relief. Now, if it be an Argument of ſuch Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in grown Perſons, why may we not allow it the like evidential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with reſpect to <hi>Children?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:37710:27"/>
            <p>It's true, Love may be cauſed by ſuch Motives, as may prove too weak a Foundation to build upon in this caſe; as when it proceeds from nearneſs of <hi>Natural Affinity,</hi> or from a ſweetneſs of Temper and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, or ſuch like common Endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. We may love good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but not as ſuch, but either as related to us in the Bonds of Nature, or as endeared to us, by their ſweet and innocent, and obliging Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny any Converſe. Now this is but a Natural Humane Love; not that <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Siritual</hi> Affection, which can yield any Concluſion, as to the good Eſtate, either of Elder or Younger Perſons. But is it Love to a <hi>Diſciple of Chriſt,</hi> as a <hi>Diſciple;</hi> Love to a good Man, as Good; a Love founded, not in <hi>Carnal</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, but <hi>Spiritual</hi> Attractives;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37710:27"/> Love to them, becauſe of their Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and as bearing the Characters of <hi>Heaven?</hi> I ſhould not doubt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe qualifications, to pronounce it a clear Argument of a <hi>Divine,</hi> and <hi>Heaven-born</hi> Principle, where-ever it is found. Love to the <hi>Image</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaks Love to the <hi>Original;</hi> Love to <hi>Saints,</hi> as ſuch, argues Love to the <hi>God of Saints,</hi> whoſe Signature and Superſcirption they bear: It's Love to Goodneſs, as Goodneſs, which argues that they have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it in themſelves; it's Love to the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> as <hi>Divine,</hi> and from <hi>Heaven;</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cannot but import ſome Lines of the ſame Nature, in the Perſon who loves.</p>
            <p>Now, what remarkable Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances have there been of this Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Affection in ſome <hi>Children!</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:37710:28"/> What pleaſing Motions of Reſpect have been ſtirr'd up in their Breaſts, upon the Sight of good People! <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.41.</note> 
               <hi>as the Babe ſprung for joy in</hi> Elizabeth's <hi>Womb, at the Salutation of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord.</hi> How glad have they been to enjoy their Company, and to hear them diſcourſe of <hi>God, and Christ, and Heaven!</hi> What a ſenſible Pleaſure have they taken, both in their Perſons and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! That we may ſay of them, as the Holy <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> once ſaid of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.3.</note> 
               <hi>They hath been the Perſons, in whom have been their principal and chief Delight.</hi> Now what Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can be made of all this, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>but that ſurely they love him that begat, who love thoſe ſo dearly that are Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of Him?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:37710:28"/>
            <p>There's a certain Inſtinct that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends <hi>Grace,</hi> as well as <hi>Nature:</hi> And as <hi>Nature</hi> will begin early to expreſs it ſelf in a tender Affection towards all the <hi>Children</hi> of the ſame <hi>Father;</hi> ſo when there is the like early Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction towards the <hi>Children</hi> of our <hi>Heavenly Father,</hi> it is an Argument, there's ſomething of that divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, which attends the new Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>It's a Character of Renown left upon <hi>Abijah,</hi> the Son of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 14.13.</note> 
               <hi>That there was found in him ſome good thing towards the Lord God of Iſrael:</hi> And this good thing is thought by ſome, to be the ſecret Countenance and Reſpect, that he ſhewed to thoſe good People, that could not comply with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Idolatry, which he had ſet up at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:37710:29"/>
            <p>Love to the <hi>People of God</hi> is Love to <hi>God himſelf at the ſecond Hand:</hi> And ſo God himſelf, tells you, that he will eſteem it at the great Day. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Macth.</hi> 25.40.</note> 
               <hi>Inaſmuch as you have done it to One of theſe, you have done it unto me.</hi> And if it will be ſo honourably owned in grown Perſons, it will ſurely be accepted and owned with no leſs Honour in <hi>Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. A delightful Appetite to the Food of <hi>Life,</hi> is another encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Symptom in <hi>Children.</hi> What an Early Deſire has appeared in ſome little Ones to the Word and Ordinances of Chriſt! Nothing has pleaſed them better, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.34.</note> 
               <hi>than to watch daily at Wiſdom's Gates, and towait at the Poſts of her Doors, where the Bread of Life uſes to be diſtributed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst hungry Souls:</hi> And what a Character the <hi>Scripture</hi> puts upon ſuch, is plain, <hi>Bleſſed are they.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:37710:29"/>
            <p>What an high Value have ſome <hi>Children</hi> ſet upon Sermons! How deſirous have they been of all Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuhities of that Nature! How ready to embrace them, when at any time offered, and unwilling to let one ſuch Seaſon ſlip, as if they eſteem'd it the loſs of a <hi>Spiritual Meal-time!</hi> With what liſtening Ears, and earneſs Looks have they been obſerved to ſit under the Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings of the Sanctuary, as if they were as greedy of the Breaſt of the Word, as the hungry Child is of the Mother's Breaſt! How ſweer and grateful have the glad Tydings of Salvation been to their tender Hearts; <hi>and with what Delight have they ſate under the Shakings of the Tree of Life,</hi> as might eaſily be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerned by their Trickling Eyes, or ſtedfaſt Looks, and pleaſing Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:37710:30"/>
            <p>Now, what does all this import, where it is found, but a Principle, fuitable to the Food, which it is carried out unto? You may know every Creature by its proper Food, which it moſt inclines unto, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in; and the new Creature is equally diſcernible by its Food. The New-born Infant no ſooner al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt makes its Appearance in the World, than it diſcovers a natural Inſtinct, leading it to the Mother's Breaſt: And may not the Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally-new-born Soul be diſcovered by the like Inclination to the ſincere Milk of the <hi>Word?</hi> So the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> plainly ſuggeſts. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>What is it that hungers and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and carries the Soul out after the <hi>Heavenly Manna?</hi> What is it that the <hi>Milk and Honey of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Land,</hi> is ſo accomodate and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37710:30"/> agreeable to? Is it any Principle of the old Nature? That cannot be, becauſe the old Nature muſt have Food ſuitable to its ſelf, ſomething Carnal and Senſual; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>For they that are in the Fleſh, ſavour only the things of the Fleſh.</hi> Therefore it muſt be ſome higher and Divine Principle; and conſequently no other than that Heaven-born Principle, which is ſtyled the new Nature.</p>
            <p>As the Food is, that is moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the Soul, ſo is the Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; and as the Inclination is, ſo is the Principle, from whence it flows.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Senſible Breathings after more Clearneſs for Heaven, do alſo adminiſter a bleſſed Ground of <hi>Hope.</hi> That <hi>Children</hi> ſhould have ſuch a Faith and Senſe of that inviſible State, as earneſtly to deſire an Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37710:31"/> a Part, a Place in thoſe <hi>Heavenly Manſions,</hi> is an Intimation of <hi>Hope,</hi> not to be deſpiſed. But when you obſerve them breathing them out of their Hearts in warm and affection<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ateſDeſires, that their Evidences were but clearer, and their Title to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven more diſtinct and legible! This cannot but miniſter a ſtill more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing Argument of <hi>Hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How ſenſibly muſt it move the tender Affections of concerned <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> to hear their <hi>Children</hi> expreſs a Thoughtful Heart about going to Heaven! But to hear them ſweetly and concernedly ſigh out, <hi>Oh that my Intereſt in Chriſt, and Right to the Heavenly Inheritance, was but more clear and evident, leſs obſcure and cloudy!</hi> This muſt make a very fenſible Addition to <hi>Parents</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Joy.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:37710:31"/>
            <p>Not to be content with a dark and doubtful Intereſt, but to ſend up fervent Groans to Heaven for more Evidence and Clearneſs; not to be ſatisfied with ſome languid Hopes, but to aſpire after a more lively and confirmed <hi>Hope,</hi> and yet in the mean time to dread Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; not to be content with ſome imperfect Dawnings of that Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Day, but to breathe after clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Diſcoveries of the Love and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God, in and through a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: This muſt certainly be a Frame of Soul, that carries not a little Encouragement in it. It's a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry encouraging Symptom in grown Perſons, and much more in <hi>Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What was it but the ſweet Breath of a Gracious Heart, when the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> addreſs'd himſelf in ſuch a Pathetick Prayer to Heaven;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37710:32"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 106.4,5.</note> 
               <hi>Remember me, O Lord, with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of thy People: Oh viſit me with thy Salvation, that I may ſee the Good of thy Choſen!</hi> Two Evidences of a Sincere Gracious Soul, are obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the Prayer: Firſt, That no leſs would ſatisfie his Panting Heart, than the Favour that was peculiar to God's own People, the good of his Choſen: And ſecondly, that could not content him neither, but he muſt have the ſenſible Refreſhing Evidence of that Favour.</p>
            <p>Such Heavenly Breathing have ſometimes appear'd in young ones; that nothing could ſatisfie them but ſome chearing Glimps of the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God; and what can be the Spring of ſuch Divine Bubblings but an Heart ſeaſon'd with an Heavenly Tincture from above? It's an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that Chriſt lies near the Heart,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37710:32"/> when the Deſires are ſo ſtrong after Clearneſs of Intereſt. <hi>Heaven</hi> muſt both be underſtood and valued, where the Soul is ſo ſollicitous for a ſure and clear Title; and would not only have ſome <hi>Hope, but rejoyce in Hope in the Glory of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. Willingneſs to be gone, to be with Chriſt, is the laſt Gracious Symptom I ſhall mention. It's not to be doubted, but Death in its ſelf muſt be as terrible to <hi>Children,</hi> as to others. The Separation of two ſuch dear Intimates, as Soul and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, cannot but look with a frightful Aſpect upon them, as well as more grown Perſons; the utter Extincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Worldly Relations, and Earthly comforts, cannot but be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unwelcome and uneaſie to Fleſh and Blood: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.11.</note> 
               <hi>To be taken from the Land of the Living, and lodged in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:37710:33"/> the Dark and hideous Manſions of the Grave, where they ſhall ſee Man no more, with the Inhabitants of the Earth,</hi> cannot but make recoil in them, as well as others. And yet it's very remarkable, how welcome this Grim and Melancholy Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger has been to ſome young Ones; and how willing have they been to leave the World, <hi>and to go to the Houſe, prepared for all Living:</hi> tho' they have but juſt begun to taſte the Sweet and Pleaſure of the World, and have felt little of the Bitter to wean their Hearts from it; yet how contented have they been to bid it Farewel, with all its Delights and Pleaſures, and have entertained <hi>Death</hi> with a very ſweet and reſigning Compoſure of Mind! Now, what could thus reconcile the King of Terrors to them, but the Thoughts
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37710:33"/> and hopes of ſomething beyond the <hi>Grave,</hi> to recompence the loſs of what they leave here? It's an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their <hi>Faith,</hi> that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a <hi>future State;</hi> and that the <hi>Happineſs</hi> thereof, infinitely exceeds all the <hi>Felicities</hi> of this preſent ſtate of <hi>Time.</hi> It's an Evidence they have got, ſome Peep within the <hi>Vail,</hi> where they have ſeen great and wonderful <hi>Things,</hi> far ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all the <hi>Enjoyments</hi> of this lower <hi>Region.</hi> It's a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their <hi>Love</hi> to, and <hi>Valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that they eſteem the <hi>Fruition</hi> of him, more worth than all the <hi>World;</hi> and are willing to be abſent from the <hi>Body,</hi> that they may be preſent with the <hi>Lord.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 5.</note> It's an argument they have ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>God,</hi> as their <hi>God,</hi> they are ſo
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37710:34"/> willing to go to Him, though it be through ſuch a <hi>Gloomy Paſſage.</hi> And that they love their <hi>Fathers Houſe,</hi> ſince the <hi>Meſſenger</hi> is ſo welcome, tho' but a frightful One, that's ſent to fetch them thither. It's an intimation they know and have felt ſomething of <hi>Heaven,</hi> when they can be ſo content, to exchange <hi>Things</hi> ſeen for unſeen; the viſible, ſenſible <hi>Comforts</hi> of this <hi>World,</hi> for the inviſible <hi>Delights</hi> of <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a Word, I'ts an evident <hi>Proof,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is their <hi>Life,</hi> their <hi>Joy,</hi> their <hi>Hope,</hi> their <hi>Happineſs,</hi> their <hi>Portion,</hi> their <hi>All,</hi> when they can ſo freely throw off all the <hi>Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi> of <hi>Fleſh</hi> and the <hi>World,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23.</note> that they may be with their Exalted <hi>Redeemer,</hi> as the beſt of all. The
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:37710:34"/> pale <hi>Horſe</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> could not meet with ſuch a welcome and ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive <hi>Reception,</hi> but that he carries them <hi>thither,</hi> whither their <hi>Hearts</hi> are already gone, And ſiher their <hi>Hearts</hi> are <hi>Above,</hi> it is an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their <hi>Treaſure</hi> is there alſo.</p>
            <p>It is, not to be expected, that <hi>Children</hi> ſhould hove ſuch clear and explicite Apprehenſions, as more mature <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, when they know ſo much, as to eſteem it a <hi>Being</hi> with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and upon that account, not only <hi>Heaven</hi> is truly deſirable, but <hi>Death</hi> is welcome, as the Way thither: it cannot but be reckon'd as a very hopeful Preſage. And what can ſuggeſt more affecting and refreſhing <hi>Hopes</hi> to <hi>Mourning Parents,</hi> than to ſee their depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:37710:35"/> 
               <hi>Children</hi> thus preter being with Chriſt before their Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in this Vain and Changeable World?</p>
            <p>Thus I have endeavoured to take afflicted <hi>Parents</hi> by the Hand, and to lead them to ſome of thoſe Cordial-Springs of <hi>Hope,</hi> which may miniſter good Encouragement as to the good Eſtate of their <hi>Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Children.</hi> And tho' it's a rare Happineſs to find all theſe Bleſſed Symptoms in a ſweet Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet where there is any of them, it may give ſome Support and Hope: And the more that appears, the higher may our Hopes advance towards an holy Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:37710:35"/>
            <p n="2">2. I come now to ſhew,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In what reſpects theſe Grounds of Hope in Dying Children, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Matter of Support and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to their Surviving Parents and Relations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Having ſuch <hi>Grounds of Hope, Parents</hi> may be ſatisfied, that their <hi>Children</hi> are not loſt, but laid up. It's a Thought, that oftentimes perplexeth the <hi>Minds</hi> of <hi>tender Parents</hi> not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, what becomes of their <hi>dear Children,</hi> when they go hence; into what Hands they fall, and whither they are tranſported and carried: And that which renders the Parting many times more Bitter and Afflictive, is the Perplexity of this. But having the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:37710:36"/> 
               <hi>Grounds of Hope,</hi> the Perplexity is preſently removed. Your <hi>Children,</hi> though gone out of your Sight and Care, yet they are not loſt, but ſafely lodg'd up: Not loſt among the <hi>Infernal A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate Fiends of Hell,</hi> thoſe <hi>Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and Murderers of precious Souls;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Malach.</hi> 3.17.</note> but ſafely laid up amongſt <hi>God's Jewels,</hi> who will have them all forth-coming another Day. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.4:</note> Not loſt in <hi>Satan</hi>'s Territories a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe raging <hi>Lyons of Prey,</hi> but happily conducted to their <hi>Heavenly Father's Boſom,</hi> where they are laid up in Peace and Safety.</p>
            <p>As God has ſtamped the Linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his own Image upon them, in True, though not in ſuch Large Characters; ſo will he not
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:37710:36"/> take care of thoſe, whom he has ſet his own Child's-mark upon? Will he loſe his <hi>Children,</hi> whom he hath adopted into the Line of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and ſet his own <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription</hi> upon, or ſuffer the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Enemy to rob him of what's ſo Dear and Precious to him? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.28,29.</note> No, no, they have all the Safety that Infinite Love, in Conjunction with Infinite Power can give them: Tho' <hi>Death</hi> have removed them from this Region of Senſible <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports</hi> and <hi>Comforts,</hi> yet <hi>Death</hi> has not put an utter end to them. They are not periſh'd by the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval,</hi> nor relaps'd into their <hi>Firſt nothing,</hi> but ſtill live in the <hi>Divine World,</hi> and another kind of Life, than they liv'd here in this Vale of <hi>Sin and Sorrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:37710:37"/>
            <p n="2">2. Having ſuch Intimations of <hi>Hope, Parents</hi> may be comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That their own Loſs is their dear <hi>Childrens</hi> Gain. We can part with our <hi>Children</hi> here, to Places and Countries at a remote diſtance, and comfort our ſelves with this, That it is for their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and Gain, though but a poor Worldly Gain. And may we not more comfortably part with them to <hi>Heaven,</hi> where their Gain infinitely exceeds any thing we can propoſe here below? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>You Tender and Sorrowful <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents;</hi> you loſe their Sweet and Delightful Company; you loſe their Charming and Refreſhing Converſe. And as a Perſon that has been conducted by the Light of a Candle in the Night, is the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37710:37"/> more ſenſible of the Darkneſs, when it is taken away; ſo it may be, you are the more over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clouded with <hi>Sorrow,</hi> by the Loſs of your <hi>Hopeful Children,</hi> after the ſweet of your Enjoyment, than if you had never enjoyed them. But do you duely conſider what you do? You think you expreſs your dear Love to them, in your Sorrow for parting with them: But ſhould not true Love oblige you, rather to rejoyce in their Gain, than to grieve for your own Loſs? Though you are Loſers, yet they are infinite Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: And ſhould not the Thought of that diffuſe a ſenſible Pleaſure into your troubled <hi>Minds,</hi> and reduce them to a Serene Calm?</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:37710:38"/>
            <p>They exchange Earthly <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> who it may be have want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no Tenderneſs towards them; but it is for an <hi>Heavenly Father,</hi> who is not only Loving, but pure and perfect Love it ſelf. They bid adieu to their Dear, but Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Friends here below; but it is to go to better, and more deſirable Friends above, where there is all Perfection and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and Harmony. They put off their filthy Garments of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Mortality; but it is to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayed with ſhining Robes of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality and Glory. They are called from a State of Sin and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and Temptation here, but it is to paſs into an endleſs State of perfect Purity and Joy in the <hi>Bleſſed Manſions above.</hi> They
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37710:38"/> are ſnatch'd out of your tender and Compaſſionate Arms; but they are received into the dearer Embraces of a <hi>Glorified Redeemer.</hi> They are taken from your Charge and Care, but they are taken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the immediate Wing and Care of a Faithful <hi>Covenant-keeping God.</hi> Oh Bleſſed Exchanged Who would not take <hi>Comfort</hi> at the Thoughts of their <hi>Children</hi> or <hi>Friends,</hi> making ſuch a Glorious and Happy Change!</p>
            <p n="3">3. Having this <hi>Hope, Parents</hi> may be ſupported, that they and their <hi>Children</hi> ſhall meet again with Rejoycing. Though you and they are ſeparated for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, yet it's not an Everlaſting Separation: You ſhall meet again, not indeed by their Return unto
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:37710:39"/> you, but by your going unto them, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.23.</note> as afflicted <hi>David</hi> comforts himſelf as to his Child: And your Meeting ſhall be in another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than now you part Your parting indeed is ſorrowful, and attended with a great deal of Bitterneſs and Exerciſe, what by dying Agonies on the one ſide, and what by cutting Reſentments on the other: But the Comfort of your Meeting will infinitely countervail the Sorrow of your parting.</p>
            <p>You part in the vile Rags of periſhing <hi>Mortality;</hi> but your Meeting will be in the <hi>Royal Robes</hi> of <hi>Immortal Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Glory:</hi> You part in Tears and Fears, and Complaints and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows; but you meet again with
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:37710:39"/> 
               <hi>Everlaſting Joy</hi> upon your Heads, with all Tears wiped from your Eyes, and with all Fears baniſh'd from your Hearts; never to ſin, never to Sorrow any more. You part, ſo as to expect to ſee one another no more in this <hi>Lower Region;</hi> but you ſhall meet again in the <hi>Coeleſtial Regions</hi> above, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be ſeparated any more, but to enjoy God, and one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God for ever: You part from one another, Mourning, though bearing your precious Seed; but you ſhall meet again, Rejoycing, bringing your full Sheaves with you. Oh Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Meeting! How reviving muſt the Thought of it be! What Mournful Breaſt is there, whoſe Soul ſprings not within him at
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37710:40"/> the Proſpect of ſuch a Meeting? Set the Joys of Meeting againſt all the Afflictive Circumſtances of Parting, and refuſe to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, it you can.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Having thus diſpatcht the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinal Part, it remains now that we make ſome ſhort Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Let me addreſs a few words to you Mournful <hi>Parents;</hi> both you, who are immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the preſent occaſion, and all others in the like caſe. Your Faces are covered with <hi>Sadneſs,</hi> and your Hearts ready to bleed within you, over the Loſs of your <hi>Dear</hi> and <hi>Hopeful Children:</hi> But let Conſideration govern your Paſſion; and while you are ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:37710:40"/> your Parental Affection in your <hi>Mourning,</hi> labour to expreſs your <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Moderation, in carrying your ſelves like <hi>Mourners</hi> of <hi>Hope.</hi> And therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Indulge not an unbounded <hi>Sorrow:</hi> For the ſame Hand that hath made you to bleed, hath not left you without an <hi>Healing Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam,</hi> ſeaſonably to cloſe up again the gaping Orifice. You need not take on, as thoſe that have no <hi>Hope,</hi> or as thoſe that have bruied their <hi>Children</hi> and their <hi>Hopes</hi> both in the ſame <hi>Grave.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.13.</note> You may not ſit down in your Deſpondency with <hi>Hagar,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.16,19.</note> as if you had no <hi>Well of Conſolation</hi> by you, when the <hi>Well</hi> is ſo near you; though your <hi>Children</hi> be gone, and gone, never to return more, yet God
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:37710:41"/> call'd them not away, till they had left with you ſome <hi>Bleſſed Pledges of Hope,</hi> to let you know whither they were a going. Tho' you are never like to ſee them, nor to hear from them, nor of them any more, till you go where they are, yet they were not ſufi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to leave you, till they had dropt ſome ſweet Tokens into your Boſom, which may be a ſenſible Support, till you meet again. And having ſuch Encouragement, does it become you to Mourn, as if the Swelling-Waves knew no Bounds?</p>
            <p>There be many that <hi>Die,</hi> who neither carry any good ground of <hi>Hope</hi> with them, nor leave any good ground of <hi>Hope</hi> behind them, to their ſurviving <hi>Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:37710:41"/> And, indeed, I ſcarce know a more humbling afflictive <hi>Caſe,</hi> that can befal <hi>Godly Perſons,</hi> then when they have the bitter Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to mourn over <hi>Hopeleſs Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> who neither had any <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> in their own <hi>Death,</hi> nor left any matter of <hi>Comfort</hi> behind them. This was probably the wounding <hi>Ingredient,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.23.</note> that made <hi>David</hi> ſo paſſionate in his <hi>Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> when he had loſt his <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom.</hi> But this is not your Caſe; though the Cloud that God has drawn over you be Dark, yet its not all Darkneſs, it has its Bright, as well as its Dark Side. And while the One miniſters matter of <hi>Sorrow</hi> to you, the reviving <hi>Beams</hi> of the Other, may give you <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Comfort,</hi> in the midſt of your <hi>Sorrows.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:37710:42"/>
            <p n="2">2. Bleſs <hi>God,</hi> that hath given you ſuch <hi>Hope,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Repining,</hi> for what you have loſt. Adore <hi>Divine Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> for what you have left you. You have loſt a <hi>Child,</hi> but you have a <hi>Legacy</hi> of <hi>Hope</hi> left you, to help you to bear your <hi>Loſs:</hi> Be more in Bleſſing <hi>God</hi> for the one, than in mourning for the other. It might have been o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe with you, that you nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther might have had <hi>Child</hi> nor <hi>Hope.</hi> But ſince <hi>God</hi> has been more gracious to you, take heed of carrying it, as if either you had no ſenſe of <hi>Divine Goodneſs,</hi> or your <hi>Relation Dyed without Hope.</hi> As there is a <hi>Debt</hi> of <hi>Tears</hi> owing to your <hi>Hopeful</hi> departed <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> ſo there is a <hi>Debt</hi> of <hi>Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:37710:42"/> owing to the <hi>God</hi> that made them ſuch. Be not over-liberal in paying the One, while in the mean time you forget the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Tho' <hi>God</hi> have taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the tender <hi>Olive-Plants,</hi> that ſhould have adorned your Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; yet (as good old <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid in another caſe) it's enough that you have a <hi>Comfortable Hope,</hi> that they are tranſplanted to a richer Table in their <hi>Father's Kingdom.</hi> They have taken their flight, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to make their Return to Earth any more: But it's enough that you have <hi>Hope</hi> in their <hi>Latter End.</hi> Bleſs God for, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort one another with that <hi>Hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Give me leave now to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove this Point more generally, to all to whom it may be uſeful; and that 1. To <hi>Parents,</hi> 2. To <hi>Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:37710:43"/>
            <p n="1">1. Here's Matter of Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to you Parents, That you would uſe the utmoſt care in the Holy Education of your <hi>Children;</hi> that whether they live or die, you may have <hi>Comfort;</hi> if they live, you may have <hi>Comfort</hi> in their Lives; if they die, you may have <hi>Hope</hi> in their Death: Or how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, you may have this Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in your own Spirits, that you have diſcharged your Duty.</p>
            <p>As ſoon therefore as they ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to a Competent meaſure of Capacity, take all Opportunities prudently to inſtil <hi>Divine Truths</hi> into their <hi>Minds,</hi> ſuch as their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Years are moſt capable of receiving; that their <hi>Minds,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo early tinctured with things of <hi>Eternal Moment,</hi> may derive
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:37710:43"/> a ſuitable Impreſſion to their <hi>Hearts.</hi> Take all convenient Seaſons to acquaint them, that there is a Great and Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, though inviſible God, who made all things, and curiouſly formed them in Secret, and form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an <hi>Immortal Spirit</hi> within them, to know and love, to live unto, and live with Him in an <hi>Everlaſting State.</hi> Be telling them, as they are able to bear, how their Natures are depraved and fallen off from their <hi>God and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs;</hi> and that thereby they are become <hi>Children of Wrath</hi> by Nature, and obnoxious to the Judgment and Curſe of an offended <hi>Majeſty.</hi> Acquaint them, with what Condeſcenſion to their Capacities you can, what guilty,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:37710:44"/> periſhing Creatures they came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, by reaſon of Sin; and if it were not for Infinite Goodneſs, that they might have been tumbled into <hi>Hell,</hi> as ſoon as ever they drew their <hi>Firſt Breath.</hi> Tell them, that in this miſerable <hi>State</hi> they might have lived and died without Remedy, had not Infinite Compaſſion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided a <hi>Saviour,</hi> to deliver poor Guilty <hi>Souls</hi> from going down to the horrible <hi>Pit.</hi> Inform them (with what plainneſs and diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs you can poſſibly uſe,) who this <hi>Saviour</hi> is, and what he has done and ſuffered, and what he is ſtill a doing, in order to the Recovery of loſt, undone <hi>Souls.</hi> Tell them, that they, even they muſt have an Intereſt in this <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:37710:44"/> or they are undone for ever; and that the way of coming to an Intereſt in Him, is by an Humble caſting themſelves upon his <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> for the Pardon of their Sins, and the Healing of their <hi>Corrupted Natures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such Truths as theſe, labour to poſſeſs, and ſeaſon their early Thoughts withal: Only, in the doing thereof, uſe all the Prudence and Gentleneſs, and Condeſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you can; that you neither overcharge them with too much at once, nor confound them with <hi>Things</hi> that their Capacities can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reach unto. And who knows how this <hi>Divine Leaven</hi> may (under the Influence of the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Bleſſing</hi>) diffuſe its powerful Vertue thro' their Tender <hi>Souls?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:37710:45"/>
            <p>As ſoon as they begin to talk, learn them to talk in the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and not of <hi>Aſhdod;</hi> in the Dialect of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and not of a <hi>Prophane World;</hi> that their early Breath be not corrupted with the rotten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of the <hi>Children of Belial.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 2.23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let it be your Pious and Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Care to teach them their <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techism,</hi> as being the moſt famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar and methodical way of Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and content not your ſelves that they learn it by rote, but labour to conveigh the Truths therein to their Underſtandings and Affections. As ſoon as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible alſo, learn them to Pray; and in order thereunto Pray with them your Selves, and acquaint
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:37710:45"/> them, both what need they have to Pray, and how they muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs themſelves to God in this Solemn Duty.</p>
            <p>Carry them, as ſoon as you can judge it convenient, to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip and Ordinances of the Goſpel; and eſteem it a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that you may carry your Young and your Old with you. Obſerve them, with what Reverence and Attention they carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, while they are there, and call them to an Account, what they have brought with them, when they come home; and take Advantage of what they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, though it be the leſs, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it to further Inſtruction.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:37710:46"/>
            <p>Above all, inure them to their <hi>Bibles</hi> betimes, and direct them to ſuch Places, as may be moſt fitted to their weak Capacities; and if in their Reading, any thing offer it ſelf, which may afford ſpecial Inſtruction to them, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it to that end. And thro' <hi>Divine Goodneſs,</hi> ſome Grains of the Immortal Seed may take Root, e're you are aware. In a word: Train them up to all Religious and Divine Exerciſes, that their tender Years are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of: And ceaſe not to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all with your <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Tears</hi> for an happy Succeſs.</p>
            <p>Would you have your <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> Comfortable in <hi>Life,</hi> and Hopeful in <hi>Death;</hi> let theſe be the Particulars of your Serious and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37710:46"/> Early Care. And the more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually to excite you thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, let me offer to you the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Coſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Without this Religious Care of Education, you cannot expect the <hi>Comfort</hi> you deſire, neither in their <hi>Life,</hi> nor <hi>Death.</hi> I know, there is nothing more Natural, than for <hi>Parents</hi> to place a great deal of <hi>Hope,</hi> and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiſe to Themſelves large ſhare of <hi>Comfort</hi> from their Riſing Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring. When you are preſſed down with the Pains, and almoſt wearied with the Care that's laid out upon them, this ſweetens and alleviates all. But ſeriouſly conſider with your ſelves, what juſt Ground have you for ſuch Expectations, without a Conſcientious Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:37710:47"/> to render them ſuch as you would have them, by an Holy Education? Can you expect to attain the End, without a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful uſe of the means, in order thereunto? Has not the Holy <hi>God,</hi> the Father of all our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> connected the Means with the End, in this, as well as other Caſes? And who dare ſeparate what God has conjoyn'd?</p>
            <p>What God may do in a way of Prerogative is one thing; and what you may expect in a way of Ordinary Diſpenſation is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. God may be Better and Kinder to your <hi>Children,</hi> than your Selves are, and may do that for them which you take no Care about. But what Warrant have you to expect this, while you
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:37710:47"/> are negligent in your Duty? Though God promiſed to do <hi>great Things</hi> for <hi>Abraham,</hi> his Friend, and for his Poſterity, yet he tells you, That in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he knew, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19.</note> 
               <hi>that</hi> Abraham <hi>would command his Children and his Houſhold to keep the way of the Lord.</hi> Intimating thereby, that he was not to expect the <hi>Comfort,</hi> without the Diſcharge of the <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> no more can you. It's in a way of diligent Performance of your Part, and in an humble De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon God for doing his Part, that you have any Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for <hi>Hope;</hi> that they ſhall be <hi>Comforts,</hi> not <hi>Croſſes</hi> to you.</p>
            <p>It's true, it's the Royal Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of a Gracious God, to give them that <hi>Grace,</hi> whereby they
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:37710:48"/> muſt be rendred comfortable, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>Life</hi> or <hi>Death:</hi> But tho' the <hi>Grace</hi> is his, the <hi>Duty</hi> is yours, and it's by the Inſtrumentality of a <hi>Gracious Education,</hi> that he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes conveys that <hi>Immortal Seed</hi> to the <hi>Soul;</hi> which though it may lie hid under the Clods for a time, yet in due Seaſon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears above Ground: Though God ſows the <hi>Seed,</hi> you may Act in a Holy Subſerviency, in Culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating the Ground, in order to a <hi>Bleſſed Crop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Without this holy Care of <hi>Education,</hi> you do not anſwer the Charge of <hi>Heaven,</hi> that's incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on you. If you are Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Parents,</hi> your Conſciences can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be affected with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, as well as your
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:37710:48"/> Hearts influenced with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of <hi>Comfort.</hi> Add this therefore to the former, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to impreſs your <hi>Spirits</hi> with the Ponderous Thoughts thereof; your <hi>Children</hi> are not ſo much yours as God's; they are not ſo much born unto You, as to the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.20.</note> 
               <hi>And as they are born un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, ſo they are given in charge to you, to train and bring up for him.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.2.</note> 
               <hi>Train up a Child in the way that he ſhould go,</hi> &amp;c. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>Ye Fathers, bring up your Children in the Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Admonition of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What can be more expreſs? Your Children are not meer Gifts, but a ſignal Truſt: You may not do with them, nor carry towards them as you pleaſe; but the Charge of <hi>Heaven</hi> is upon You to Educate
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:37710:49"/> and breed them up for the God that gave them. And how will you anſwer your Neglect to the Great and Sovereign Law-giver, if you live either in the Wilful or Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Violation of ſo Solemn a Charge? Or, with what Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can You expect <hi>Comfort,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their Enjoyment, or in their Removal, if You be guilty of a provoking Diſobedience to ſo plain a Command? Can God be pleaſed with ſuch <hi>Parents,</hi> or can You expect that He ſhould make Your <hi>Children</hi> pleaſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Without this Pious Care of Education, you do not anſwer your Care for them in other Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars: You are careful to Feed and Cloath them, without need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:37710:49"/> any Arguments to preſs you thereunto. You can take Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of their <hi>First capacity,</hi> to learn them ſome External Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilities, and to form their flexible Years into ſome Decenoy of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, which you call good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. You are careful to provide, not only for their preſent, but for their future Livelihood, and to breed them up to ſome way of Comfortable Subſiſtence in the World, as your Abilities, and their Capacity will admit. And while all this Care is beſtowed upon the Outward Man, ſhould there not be a proportionable Concern for the better part? Should the One in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſs all, and the Other be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected as a Matter of no great Moment? Our <hi>Saviours</hi> Rule
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:37710:50"/> is; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.36.</note> 
               <hi>Seek firſt the Kingdom of God, and the Righteouſneſs thereof, and all other things ſhall be added unto you. Seek first for the Kingdom of God;</hi> and if for your ſelves, then for you <hi>Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which ſhould challenge the higheſt Care, but the beſt Part, whether of our ſelves, or <hi>Children?</hi> And, whether is the better; the External, Mortal part, or the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Immortal Spirit? Whether is the more Valuable; their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, Temporary Being? If Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity be of more Importance than Time, then ſurely their Eternal State ſhould be the largeſt Sharer in your Thoughts and Cares; or how will you anſwer the Ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality? You would have them do well in this World, that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:37710:50"/> is the Motive of all the Thought and Pains, and Expence, which you beſtow upon their Outward Being. And would you not have them to do well in the <hi>Eternal World?</hi> Why then does not your Care for that bear ſome Proportion to your Concern for the other? You eſteem it a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, and a moſt Becoming Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of <hi>Parental</hi> Affection, to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and endeavour their Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Welfare. And ſo it is. But ſhould not Your Love travel in more earneſt Endeavours and Agonies for that which is infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly better; the Everlaſting hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of their <hi>Immortal Souls?</hi> Whether ſhould be Dearer to you, the <hi>Cabinet</hi> or the <hi>Jowel?</hi> The Periſhing Earthly
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:37710:51"/> 
               <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> or the <hi>Ineſtimably precious Soul?</hi> How then will you anſwer it, either to your own Conſciences, or to the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Judge;</hi> if you are more Liberal in your Care about the Worſe, than the Better part?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Without a Conſcientious Care of Education, your Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will be doubled in their Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage: As they are ſo Near and Dear unto you, you cannot but be deeply afflicted, if either they ſhould prove Croſſes in <hi>Life,</hi> or ſhould be ſnatch'd away in their Sins by a Premature Death: But what a cutting Addition will it be to your Affliction, if you have Reaſon to accuſe your ſelves, as being Acceſſory to their Ruin by your Sinful negligence! It will be
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:37710:51"/> Grief enough, to think that you have nouriſhed and brought up <hi>Children</hi> for the <hi>Deſtroyer:</hi> But it will be a far more ſenſible Grief, when you are forced to take the Guilt of their undoing very much upon your ſelves, for want or a due Performance of your Doby to them. It cannot but go very near your Hear as, that thoſe, who are as it were Limbs, and Pieces of your ſelves, ſhould become a Prey to the oruel Murtherer; but it muſt break your hearts to the very Duſt, when by your own Neglect you have as it were murdered them with your own Hands; or at leaſt have not done what in you lay to ſave them from the <hi>Murtherer</hi>'s <hi>Hands.</hi> That you have neither <hi>Comfort</hi> in their
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:37710:52"/> Life, nor <hi>Hope</hi> in their Death, will be Sorrow and Bitterneſs enough: But when your own Conſciences fall upon you with the outting Reflection, that all this is but the ſad Fruit of your own Remiſneſs and Negligence, how will you he able to bear a Charge of ſo wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Nature?</p>
            <p>If they ſhould prove uncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table or unhopeful, after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Diſcharge of your Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, though your Affliction will be great, yet you will have one Support at leaſt under your Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: You may comfort your ſelves, that you have diſcharged your Duty; and it is not thro' your Default, that they Periſh; and though they miſs of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of your Cares, and Prayers,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:37710:52"/> and Endeavours, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.13.</note> yet the Bleſſing may return in your own Boſom; but if you contribute to their Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage, by your neglecting the appointed Means of <hi>Heaven,</hi> for the Prevention thereof, your Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den may weigh heavier, than you will be able to bear. Why might not this be one imbittering Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in <hi>Davids</hi> Sorrow, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.33.</note> that might cauſe him to take on ſo heavily at the Death of his Son <hi>Abſalom?</hi> Poſſibly he might be under ſome bitter Reflections of his own Fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure in his Duty; which might make the Stroke pierce ſo deep: And it will be no leſs an Aggravation of your Bitterneſs, if it ſhould prove your caſe.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:37710:53"/>
            <p>
               <hi>But thus much may ſerve to Partents, who would have Hope in their Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I come now to direct my ſelf in a few Words to You <hi>Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have heard how much your <hi>Parents Comfort</hi> is bound up in the Proof of your Blooming Years; labour therefore after that which may afford the moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Conſolation, both to Your ſelves and them, whether in <hi>Life</hi> or <hi>Death.</hi> Next, to their own <hi>Souls,</hi> you are the great Object of your <hi>Parent</hi>'s <hi>Cares and Fears,</hi> of their Prayers and Thoughts of Heart: And if God ſhould ſee
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:37710:53"/> meet to pluck you away in the Bud, you had need to make your Death as comfortable, both to your ſelves, and your concerned <hi>Parents,</hi> as you can. It will be Sorrow e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to them, to part with you, when they ſhould come to enjoy the ſweeteſt and moſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of your Life: You had need to make it as eaſie as you can, by leaving them ſome <hi>Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pledge</hi> of <hi>Hope</hi> behind you.</p>
            <p>And that you may do ſo, I cannot give you more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Advice than now in your Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-years to look after the beſt things, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.9.</note> 
               <hi>even the things that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany Salvation.</hi> I ſuppoſe you to be capable of apprehending and enquiring into things of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: Know therefore, that you,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:37710:54"/> as little and young as you are, have a Real and Everlaſting Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern in ſuch things, as well as others: And it's not too ſoon for you to take your ſelves to be concerned about them. Now, to enquire after God, and to mind the things of your Peace, is God's Call to you, as well as more grown Perſons. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>Remember now thy Creator in the days of thy Youth.</hi> Obſerve the little Word, <hi>now;</hi> it takes date from the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-Twilight of your Day, as ſoon as your Rational Powers peep forth into Competent Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe: And from the time it takes date, it admits of no delay. Now remember: Now delay not; for you cannot aſſure your ſelves of another Moment. Say not,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:37710:54"/> 
               <hi>It will be time enough to Morrow;</hi> for to Morrow, as ſhort a time as it ſeems to be, you know not, but you may be under the Arreſt of <hi>Death,</hi> and ready to be ſhut up in your ſilent Grave, <hi>where there is no Wiſdom nor Knowledge.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10.</note> Say not, <hi>Such work will be more proper for Riper Years:</hi> For who can give you aſſurance, that you ſhall live to more Maturity? <hi>Death</hi> comes not by Order of Nature, but according to the <hi>Divine Commiſſion.</hi> As Young and Sprightly as you are, and as many Daysas you ſeem to have before you, yet for ought you know, your Glaſs may be running out its laſt Sand: And this may be the laſt Month, or Week, or Day, that you have to live. As
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:37710:55"/> young as you are gone to the cold <hi>Manſions in the Grave;</hi> and what Security have you from the fatal Stroke, more than they? Go into the Shops, and ſee if there be no <hi>Coffins</hi> of your ſize: Go into the <hi>Church yard,</hi> and ſee if there be no <hi>Graves</hi> of your Length. If there be, as your own Eyes will ſoon convince you, conſider with yourſelves, that a few Moments may bring it to your Turn. And then, how comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble will it be, both to your ſelves and Friends, that you have ſo Early ſecured your Everlaſting In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt! Your <hi>Parents</hi> will be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able to part with you, when your Early Goodneſs gives them Hopes, that you are going to a better, an Infinitely better Father.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:37710:55"/> And you your, ſelves will more Comfortably ſhoot the Diſmal Gulph, when you have Reaſon to believe, that you have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your Souls into thoſe Bleſſed Hands, that will land them ſare on the other ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In order hereunto, let me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendun to you a few ſeaſonable Inſtructions, and beg of you to put them into ſerious and ſpeedy Practiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Begin to entertain your Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Thoughts with Soul-Matters: God having Mercifully preſerved you beyond the Incapacity of your Infant-Age; and having brought you to ſome Competency of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; it's time for you to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:37710:56"/> apply your ſcrious Thoughts to things of the moſt concernful Moment. And what can be of more Indiſpenſable Moment, than the Everlaſting Concerns of your <hi>precious Souls?</hi> It's not too ſoon for you to know, that you have <hi>Immortal Souls</hi> in your Boſoms, which though Inviſible to an <hi>Eye of Senſe,</hi> yet are not only Real, but the moſt Precious and Valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Part of your ſelves: It's not too early for you to underſtand and conſider, that theſe <hi>Spiritual Beings</hi> are formed on purpoſe for an Everlaſting State; and that when the <hi>Dreggy Carcaſſes</hi> are thrown to the Duſt, yet theſe <hi>Immortal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> ſurvive to paſs into the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible World,</hi> there to be the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of unexpreſſible happineſs,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:37710:56"/> or Miſery for ever. It's not improper nor impertinent for you to lay to Heart, that Eternity muſt be of greater Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance than Time; and that the State, which muſt laſt for ever, is of more abſolute neceſſity, than that which is but like to laſt for a few Days.</p>
            <p>Let it be your endeavour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to apply your Early Thoughts to ſuch things as theſe; inſtead of ſuffering them to be carried away with thoſe Vanities, which too ordinarily get the ſtart of more ſerious Matters. It's impoſſible for you to be truly Religious, till you begin to be ſerious Think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as you may ſee in the Inſtance of the <hi>Prodigal Son.</hi> And what more meet, more proper, more
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:37710:57"/> concerning, to entertain Your firſt Thoughts with, than what we are, and what will become of us for ever? What are we? <hi>Bruits,</hi> that have only a <hi>Life of Senſe;</hi> or Reaſonable, Underſtanding Creatures? What will become of us? Shall we periſh with the Beaſts, and there be end of us, or ſhall we live beyond the <hi>Grave?</hi> And, if we muſt ſurvive the <hi>Grave,</hi> what will be Our Condition in that <hi>Future State?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such Thoughts as theſe will neither be unbecoming, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary, as Young as you are. And your Thoughts, by thus looking Inwards, will by a neceſſary Connexion, be led to look Upwards. By thinking of your ſelves, you will be led
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:37710:57"/> to think and conſider of <hi>God,</hi> as the <hi>Author</hi> of your <hi>Beings,</hi> as the great <hi>Object</hi> of your <hi>Duty,</hi> as the Awful <hi>Judge,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom you muſt ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a few Days; and as the <hi>Bleſſed Center,</hi> where alone you can expect <hi>Reſt</hi> and <hi>Happineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How profitably, how ſweetly may your Thoughts run up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe Subjects! And how re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing will it be to your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting <hi>Parents,</hi> to obſerve, that you are Thoughtful about ſuch Matters?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Labour to poſſeſs your Hearts with the Early Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your Miſerable <hi>State</hi> by Nature. As innocent as you may ſuppoſe your ſelves to be, yet be
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:37710:58"/> willing to know, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>That by nature you are Children of Wrath, as well as the worſt of Sinners,</hi> and that you came into the World with that Corruption and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filement of Nature, which renders you Guilty before God. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19.</note> Be willing to be convinced, that you are ſo many undone, periſhing Souls, whom God is angry with every day, and who are obnoxious to his <hi>Righteous Judgment,</hi> every moment, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.36.</note> 
               <hi>till a Change of State have paſt upon you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Look within you, and ſee what wretched depraved Creatures Sin hath made you: Full of little, but Rebellion and Enmity againſt <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Serious Goodneſs.</hi> Look above you, and ſee the <hi>Flaming Sword of Offended Juſtice,</hi> wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:37710:58"/> only for a <hi>Divine Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to diſlodge your Trembling Souls out of your Bodies, and to ſend you down to the <hi>Chambers of Death.</hi> Look before you, and behold the <hi>Burning Lake</hi> of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wrath,</hi> opening her <hi>Mouth</hi> to receive you into <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nquencha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Flames.</hi> And having got a ſight of your Danger and Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, argue the Caſe with your own Souls; Is this a Condition to be reſted or lingred in? Is this a State to be careleſs, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned about? <hi>Who can dwell with Conſuming Fire? Who can in hub it with Everlaſting Burnings?</hi> Why art thou at eaſe, O my Soul? Why art thou ſecure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me? Thy caſe is thus Dreadful and Dangerous.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:37710:59"/>
            <p>Sequeſter ſome of the Time, which is too often ſpent in Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to entertain your Minds with ſuch Conſiderations and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulations, as theſe; and put not off the matter with a few ſlight Thoughts, that almoſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in the Thinking; but labour to preſs and follow the Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, till your Awakned Souls begin to cry out, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16.30.</note> 
               <hi>Oh! what ſhall we do to be ſaved?</hi> What bleſſed News will it be to your Concerned <hi>Parents,</hi> to hear from you ſuch an Enquiry!</p>
            <p n="3">3. Endeavour to impreſs your Hearts with your abſolute need of a <hi>Saviour.</hi> You muſt know, You cannot be ſaved now, but in an humble Compliance with
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:37710:59"/> the Terms of the Goſpel no more than others; and that muſt be by looking after Pardoning and Healing <hi>Grace</hi> in a <hi>Redeemer;</hi> pardoning <hi>Grace,</hi> to deliver you from the Condemnation; Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Grace,</hi> to deliver you from the Dominion of <hi>Sin.</hi> Be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that nothing ſhort of this <hi>Grace</hi> can ſavingly recover you; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>And that this Grace is not to be had, but in a Mediator.</hi> Make it therefore the matter of your Early Inquiry, who this <hi>Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> is, what he hath done and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and purchaſed for you, and how you muſt come to an Intereſt in Him and His <hi>Glorious Purchaſes.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:37710:60"/>
            <p>When you hear the Tydings of this <hi>Beloved Saviour,</hi> attend thereunto, as thoſe that are ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that you have as Needful a Concern in Him as any. When he is propoſed and tender'd to you upon Goſpel-terms, know that your Conſent is expected, as well as from others; and that now you are paſt your <hi>Infant-ſtate,</hi> you muſt be ſaved in the very ſame way, and by the very Rules, as Older Perſons. Is a Cordial Acceptation of Chriſt, as their onely <hi>Lord and Saviour</hi> required of others? The ſame is expected from you. Is a Sincere Reſignation of themſelves to be entirely the Lord's, required of others? The very ſame is call'd for from you, without any Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:37710:60"/> or Diſpenſation. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. from the 22<hi>th ver.</hi> to the end. Labour to ſettle theſe things upon your Hearts betimes, for they are your Life.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Apply your ſelves to a ſerious Reading the <hi>Scriptures</hi> and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance upon Publick <hi>Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> As ſoon as you have learnt to read, put your ſelves to Chriſt's School, and let the <hi>Bible</hi> be the chief Book you deſire to learn in. The <hi>Scriptures</hi> are for your Inſtruction as well as for Others: Read them, not meerly as a Task, but as the matter of your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light; not to gratiſie your Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>but as the Bleſſed Means to make you wife unto Salvation.</hi> Here, as in a Glaſs, you muſt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:37710:61"/> behold your own Wretchedneſs and Miſery: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.23. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</note> And here alſo you muſt behold the Matchleſs Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Excellency of a <hi>Redeemer.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16,17.</note> In this Chryſtal Mirrour you muſt ſee <hi>Sin</hi> to be exceeding ſinful; and here alſo you muſt ſee <hi>Christ</hi> to be exceeding Precious. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is neceſſary, either to your preſent Duty, or future Felicity, muſt be all learnt from hence. Make this bleſſed Book then your Early Companion; it's a Book to make you Wiſe, as well as more grown Perſons; and you cannot be too ſoon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it.</p>
            <p>And the better to promote your Acquaintance therewith, and Improvement thereby, put your ſelves betimes under the Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:37710:61"/> of publick Ordinance. Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Ordinances muſt help on Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Duties: The Divine Truths, that you read in private, may be more opened and applied with that <hi>Heavenly Light</hi> and <hi>Warmth,</hi> as may not only enlighten your Underſtandings, but inflame your Affections with an Holy Life and Love: I Let it be your Delight then, as ſoon as you are capable <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.34.</note> 
               <hi>to wait daily at Wiſdom's Oates, and to wait at the Posts of hat Doors.</hi> And wait with all Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Reverence, with an earneſt Deſire and Expectation of the Coming down of the <hi>Angel,</hi> to heal your Souls, and to make you Sound and Sincere Converts.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:37710:62"/>
            <p n="5">5. Send up your early Cries to <hi>Heaven,</hi> that you may not fail of the <hi>Grace of God.</hi> During your uncapable Infancy, your <hi>Parents</hi> have prayed for you; now you muſt pray for your ſelves. And you have both as much need, and as many Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to Pray as others. You have as much Need to Pray as Others: For being Guilty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, you ſtand in need of Pardoning Mercy; and your Natures being depraved, you ſtand in need of Regeneration by the <hi>Spirit of Grace,</hi> as well as others. And who are more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to Pray for theſe <hi>Divine bleſſings</hi> for you, than you are for your ſelves? Or who have a nearer Concern in you, than
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:37710:62"/> you have in your deareſt ſelves? You have alſo as many Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements to Pray as Others: For beſides the bleſſed Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements, common to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of <hi>Seekers</hi> in general, you have Special and Appropriate Promiſes to encourage you. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.17.</note> 
               <hi>I love them that love me; and they that ſeek me early ſhall find me.</hi> Early Seekers are the ſureſt Find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. And who would not ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſo Bleſſed a Duty, that have ſuch Encouragements of Success?</p>
            <p>Learn then to make your humble Addreſſes to the <hi>throne of Grace</hi> betimes; and though you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Pray as you would, yet ſtrive to Pray as well as you can. Preſs your Hearts with the Senſe of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:37710:63"/> your Wants; and that will direct you to ſuch Expreſſions, as will be acceptable to God, though they may but be Poor and Confuſed in themſelves. If you can ſay little, yet ſend up your Sighs and Groans; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.</note> and that Broken, Inar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulate language may have Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer with God, and prevail. When you can do no more, tell him in all Humility, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 23.26.</note> that you are reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to hang at his Door, and lie at his Foot until he bleſs you. Oh! howgrateful muſt it be, both to <hi>Heaven and Earth,</hi> to ſee you ſo Early in your <hi>Bibles,</hi> and upon your Knees, breathing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt, and enquiring the Way to the <hi>Heavenly Zion!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:37710:63"/>
            <p>This is now Early Religion: This is the Holy Courſe I would recommend to your Blooming Years, both for your own and your <hi>Parent</hi>'s ſake. The Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance whereof will be your Crown and Joy, whether you live or die. If you live to arrive to more Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity, it will be your Glory and Honour, that you have began ſo Early with God, as well as you <hi>parents</hi> Delight and Joy: And if you die in your tender Minority, it will both be your own Peace, and your <hi>Parent</hi>'s <hi>Comfort</hi> in your <hi>Latter End.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
